♪ [music] ♪
[waves crashing]
[birds chirping]
- [Amie] My life looked pretty good.
Two and three vacations a year,
and the house, the kid, the dog,
the husband.
But I was certainly feeling unfulfilled,
looking for something more.
♪[music]♪
People that don't know about second life,
they call it a game,
but I think that word
just doesn't do it justice.
It is a community and for me,
it's a conduit to meet
with someone very special.
I'm gonna have to ask you
to leave that. Aaahh, sorry!
♪[music]♪
- [Steven] I've been married 20 years.
She's, I think, it's 11 years,
and then we found each other.
[typing sound]
I live in Calgary, Alberta in Canada
and she lives in New York.
We met somewhere like
in the end of December.
I think just before the New Year.
♪[music]♪
Her avatar was plain compared to others
but it was the conversation
that changed it all.
It's pretty exciting.
I mean, talk about love as a drug.
I use the term "Emotional Adultery"
because real world's hung up
about physical sex
but what's really more important is
the emotional attachment
you have with someone.
Our real life partners,
really don't know what we're up to.
As far as they're concerned it's just
some kind of game that we play.
♪ [music] ♪
- Excuse me, where are you
coming in from?
- I'm coming from Atanta.
- Okay, thank you.
- What flight was this please?
- This is a flight from West Palm Beach.
- Okay, thank you.
- Okay? Thanks.
- Well, how are you?
Nice to see you.
- I think I recognize you.
- Yeah.
[Laughing]
Ahh, right now, we're going out
to my car rental.
so, I think it's automatic.
We're gonna cross.
- I can't believe any of this.
I can't believe this.
- I know. I know.
- This is crazy.
I gotta collect my thoughts.
[Giggles]
- It's a relief that when we finally meet
that she is who she says she is.
And even more beautiful than I imagined.
*- [Philip Rosedale] Second Life's different
than a game because there isn't any goal.*
And it has the very unusual property
that everything in it is changeable.
And if fact, is created by the people
who are there, not by us, the company.
In fact, we didn't build anything
in the Second Life.
It started out as just a small island
with some trees on it.
♪ [music] ♪
*And as residents came in, they began,*
*you know, buying and, you know*
*developing that space.*
*So, literally, clearing the trees*
*and building houses on it.*
They started building the content,
*like glasses or clothes or tables or chairs*
*or guns or cars.*
We didn't build any of that.
We simply built a technology platform.
*Think of it as being
much like the web, you know.*
*We created the server space*
*and the software running on the servers*
*that will allow you to basically*
*go in there and make web pages*
*only you're not making web pages,*
*you're making reality.*
[women chattering]
*People inevitably, you know,*
*approach it with a "how could that be"*
*kind of a question*
*or how could the virtual world be real?*
But, I think in the years to come,
we'll realize that
the question was more just, why not?
*- [Rohan Barnett] The AvaStar
is a tabloid newspaper.*
We cover news, business, fashion,
celebrities, travels,
all sorts of these tabloid themes.
However, we only cover Second Life.
*So, all our content was
based on Second Life.*
*At the beginning, when we
first looked at Second Life,*
76% of Second Life were from America.
Now, you have over 60%
coming from Europe.
*Registered people that actually come
and got themselves*
*an avatar is at seven million*
*So, you're definitely seeing a massive
expansion in Second Life population.*
- One of the fastest growing sites on the
internet is a 3D world called Second Life.
- It's been a massive hype. It's been all over
the media and in the newspapers,
*definitely on television.*
- Second Life is not a game.
It's a multi-user virtual environment.
It doesn't have points or scores.
It doesn't have winners or losers.
- Oh, there's losers.
- This is supposed to be me, kind of.
It's called an avatar.
And it's part of a world
some people call very cool,
while others consider it very weird.
- Second Life now is sort of where
the world wide web was at about 1994.
People are starting to discover it.
*- Wednesday, a psycho celebrityis dead.*
- She doesn't seem real, does she?
- She made herself look like her avatar.
*- [TV Host] Please join me in giving
a warm, digital welcome*
*to Bruce, we dubbed, Willis.*
*Welcome Bruce.*
- Hi. How are you doing?
- People don't just engage in perverse
sexual activity in Second Life,
but they also engage in forms
of artistic expression or commerce.
- There are so many big brands
that have come into Second Life.
*Massive multinationals, big companies*
*coming in and experimenting,*
*getting feedback on their products.*
*The question is,*
*can Second Life make this progression*
*to becoming a mass portal in the future?*
And of course that's unclear.
*- [Philip] I think that what we look back
on now in Second Life*
*will have been the beginning of a proof on that.*
Things are real because they're there
with us and we believe in them.
And if they're simulated on a
digital computer
versus sort of simulated by
atoms and molecules,
it doesn't make any difference to us.
- My name is Asri Falcone and
I am a content creator within Second Life.
I have a housing company and
we create fully furnished homes.
So, when you come into this home,
there is nothing you need.
There is nothing you need to buy
— extra furniture, nothing.
You can just move right on in
to your dream home.
And we specialize in high-end
and extreme luxury.
*You can actually have the house
of your dream within Second Life*
*without the real life price.*
♪[music]♪
-Asri Falcone is a mirror image.
I don't role play Asri.
Asri is not my alter-ego. Asri is....
me.
- My avatar is an 11-year old girl.
And I had no idea that she would turn out
that way, as I started creating her.
But, suddenly, she took on
a life of her own.
The first night was — I always say
it was like taking the red pill.
It was like everything that had
happened up to the point
where I had started her journey,
I can forget.
- [Fiancée] I remember him telling me
about something,
some virtual world called Second Life.
And, you know, that was completely
new to me. I'd heard nothing of it.
I didn't even know
what a virtual world was.
One night, he brought
the computer into bed.
- The first night I kept going
until the sun came out.
And I noticed it was
eight in the morning.
That was the first time
I looked at the clock
and I had no idea how
an entire night could pass.
- And I looked over and said,
"What are you doing?
And then I turned back
and went right back to sleep.
- The moment there was downtime
I logged in again
and it was after going
for another night.
I'm going for days straight
that the other things
just weren't important anymore.
*Sleeping was absolutely
out of necessity*
*when I really had no other choice
and it was just for a couple of hours.*
It was a physical feeling.
It was a mental feeling
And it affected everything about me
and everything about the way I acted.
[Girl giggling]
I felt like --
*she was very familiar and some dude
that I'd always known.*
*It was some sort of exploration
of something in my subconscious.*
*- [Fiancée] We were up Barnes and Noble*
*and he was looking at
the psychologist, Carl Jung.*
And he said something about, you know,
how sort of how there's a male
in every female
and a female in every male
concept that Jung has
and that he has created a girl avatar.
And I said, "Well, why?
What do you do with the girl avatar?"
And then he revealed to me that
she was a child
and how that that's
usually frowned upon.
And I remembered thinking,
"Well, I can see why."
♪[music]♪
*- She loves to dance.*
*That's been sort of her calling in life*
*and Second Life is a great place
for dancing.*
I think of myself as an observer,
maybe sort of a driver
because she's guiding me.
She knows what she wants
me to do and I do it.
♪[music]♪
[waves crashing]
[kids yelling]
- [Amie] Life is in the way of living happily
ever after - real life, you know.
While it's our goal, I guess
to not remain in Second Life
but to have meetings in real life
and I guess eventually,
get together in real life.
You know, we have other lives. I am...
I don't wanna say it.
[Steven laughing]
Why don't you say it?
It's gonna ruin my day.
- You know, we each have families now
that have nothing to do with
our Second Life relationship.
And, you know, here we are.
Our Second Life
is transposing into real life.
So, we have to somehow
reconcile our real life
with our Second Life to our new real life.
[Snoring]
[Alarm beeping]
- Where is it?
My day begins as I wake up,
probably around 6 PM.
And I usually like to start
and work at night,
overnight to 10, 11 AM.
*And I do that because
during that time of day,*
you don't have too many
people bothering you.
You don't have the phone calls
coming in, the distractions.
So, I can totally concentrate
on exactly what I need to do.
I'm usually on my computer,
anywhere from 15 to 20 hours a day,
with a pack of cigarettes in between.
[laughs]
The way I got into SL was a fluke.
A friend of mine in a different game said,
"Hey, why don't you come on over?"
"I know this game where you can
build things and you came make things."
And so I tried it.
And I have not come out
since that first day.
*You build things in Second Life
using what they call* primitives.
*Primitive is the basic building block of SL.
And they can be cut or twisted*
*or hollowed out
to make different shapes.*
*You take those shapes,
you put them together*
*like building blocks that you had as a kid.*
*And you can make your table
or your hot air balloon,*
*or anything that you want.*
*Anything that you can think of
you can actually build.*
I made my first product
my first day online.
*We were walking around and I saw
beautiful gowns that were just gorgeous,*
*and I wanted one so bad.*
*But I was a newbie, I had no money.
So, I decided to make it.*
And that's pretty much
how I make my line.
If I want to wear it, I make it.
If I want to live in it, I make it.
*I have a clothing store where people
can actually come in*
*and peruse my virtual clothing line.*
- [Asri] Hi Hon, is there anything
I can help you find?
- Hi Miss Asri. How are you doing?
- Well, I'm looking for something
that will fit my size
because I have difficulty finding
things that, you know, stretch properly.
- [Asri] Well, all of my skirts
do come modifiable.
- [Customer] Oh, that is wonderful.
- [Asri] So, well yeah, I actually have
a larger figure on the bottom myself.
- [Customer] Okay.
- [Asri] So, therefore, you know,
let's try to find you something.
*They can shop.*
*They can really customize your avatar*
*to exactly what you want it to be.*
*My skin line, which is called Nakid,*
*cost around a thousand Lindens*
*which is approximately,
I say about $3.50 US.*
*On the other hand, you have
my clothing line which things range*
*anywhere from 800 Lindens on
down to 50 Lindens.*
*When you receive that virtual currency,*
*you could actually sell it back*
*on a virtual money market.*
*In this case, you're exchanging
Linden Dollars to US Dollars*
♪[music]♪
- How cool is that? Honestly, I get paid
to play video games all day.
How cool is that?
- Everything is very real in my mind.
In fact, you know,
the Second Life stuff included,
and it's not like I don't have a grasp
on reality. I very much do.
But my memories of Steven,
our time together with Steven,
the way I would characterize Steven
and the wonderful things he's done.
They haven't all been real life
when I go over those in my mind.
I realize that I'm pulling
many real life memories
but also several Second Life memories,
of times that we shared in Second Life.
That's really kind of bizarre but they're
as much a part of my memory
and understanding of Steven
as the real ones.
[typing on keyboard]
- Kiss me you fool.
- A-huh.
- Oh, Steven.
There is little private rooms too, around.
I think, I'd love to check those out.
Ohhh, check this out.
[waterfalls gurgling]
♪ [music] ♪
- You want to time your breathing
with your movements.
- [foreign language]
- Okay.
- Uhmm.
- It's inhale as you expand,
exhale as you contract.
This is, I think, we should
drop down to our loin cloths and...
- Yeah.
- You see this. We just build up our
state of mind going through this posture
for 15 or 20 minutes and
then we jump on to the bed.
- Uhmm.
- I would like to do some deep breathing,
with you darling.
- Uhmm.
Oh, cool.
Oh, gosh. You know, like I swear
I can feel your breath on —
like I could hear it in my ear.
- Yeah.
- I can feel it in my hair
and kind of the warmth. I swear it.
- Uhmm.
- Okay, come on to the green balls here.
[Amie giggling]
[Moaning]
- Hello!
- And I feel very naked.
- You are.
[frog croaks]
♪[music]♪
*- Ayya quickly re-established herself*
*as something of a different child*
*And there are individuals who have families*
*and individuals at the school who don't.*
♪[music]♪
[footsteps]
*She's not gotten herself invited over
to slumber parties or anything like that*
*but she will often go off on adventures
with one or two other kids*
*and they'll start traveling to different
places looking for fun stuff to do.*
[footsteps]
*You've got to assume that all of the
child avatars in Second Life are adults*
*because it's illegal for children
to enter Second Life.*
[child laughing]
*There are many adoption centers.*
*It's a place where a child can go
to be matched*
*with a parent and vice-versa.*
*And interestingly, the adoption centers
are mostly girls.*
[Girl giggling]
*There's so many complex reasons
why people would want to do*
*Second Life as a child.*
I'm not there for sexual reasons at all.
But, there's a lot of older men,
a lot of married men —
straight married men
who are in Second Life
to play gay boys, for whatever reason
and very often they don't know
themselves why.
- He has an addictive personality.
and this could very easily
become a problem, if it isn't already.
He's spending a lot of time
on Second Life.
I think it becomes a problem
when you ignore your first life.
He used to be able to work
in his office with the door open
and I could pop in
and we could have a conversation
or we could, you know,
he could take a break
and we could go do something.
And suddenly, when he was
on Second Life
the door was closed
and there was a different feel.
*When the door is closed I just assume*
*that he's either working on something*
*that's very important that he needs
to focus on*
*or more likely he is on Second Life.*
*And chances are he is
with the female avatar.*
And since he knows
that I don't want to know much about it,
I think he assumes that at this point
he should keep it to himself.
- I've actually asked her
if she's ready to hear a little bit more
or if she wants to see a little bit of it
and she's still not ready.
She still doesn't want to,
she might never be.
- He says he's getting something
out of having a female child avatar
I'm not certain as to what that is,
but he says he's getting something
out of it.
[typing on keyboard]
- Whenever I'm on Second Life as Ayya
she feels alive and it just feels real.
And it feels like a real life
and life takes time.
[wind blowing]
[typing on keyboard]
Almost always
something interesting happens
and you never know
who's gonna be on.
You never know
what they're gonna be doing.
[typing on keyboard]
[waves crashing]
[child laughing]
[typing on keyboard]
One of the things that I learned from her
is that nothing is ever enough.
And nothing was ever enough for her,
her family, her friends,
and the things she was doing.
She always wanted more
and she always wanted new things.
And she never stopped
and finished anything.
By watching her go through that
over and over again,
and never be happy with what she had,
I was able to see that I am
exactly the same way.
And that's how I moved from
having this great real life,
which is amazing and
I was very thankful for
to pursuing this Second Life
for this other part of me
that I really didn't have time for.
I'm putting everything at risk right now,
my family, and my future, and my job
and even my health, probably because
I don't sleep very much.
I know I'm at a critical point
where I can't —
it's not gonna, it's not gonna
go on forever
I'm not gonna be able
to cover it up forever.
- [Asri] Well, I'm Asri Falcone.
How are you doing?
Can I help you guys find anything?
- [Customer] We're just looking.
I have several houses.
I have the big blue one.
I have the ranch in style.
[Laughs]
- [Asri] But we have a couple
of new ones coming out shortly.
- [Customer] Yeah, I was just
showing them this house.
Yeah, 'cause I'm thinking of the house
I wanna put up on my land again.
- [Asri] Did you try —
did you check out the depot?
- [Customer] Yeah, I was looking
at that but I have kids, great kids.
- [Asri] Oh, Lord.
*- [Customer] They all seem to think
they need a room.*
- [Little Girl] Ahuh!
[Laughing]
- Hello, family.
- Hi, Tea.
- Hello, Tea.
- Hey, mom. What have we got?
- Well, right now, I live with my parents
and one of my brothers.
- I can't find my keys.
*- [Tea] Oh, that might help.*
*- [Mom] You went downstairs.
That would help.*
*- [Tea] I came home from college,
quite a few years ago*
and moved back to help around here
because both of them kind of got ill
at the same time.
And because of my mom's cooking
I've never left. [laughing]
We just are really close family.
So, living under the same roof,
we help out each other a lot.
And I've been sick on and off
for the last few years,
so it goes both ways.
- We don't know her by her online entity.
We know her as our baby sister.
So, we call her Tea or TC.
- She's out-going. She is quirky.
She is funny. She is artistic.
And she demonstrates all
the artistic qualities
of a person who lives her life that way.
- When I had my graphic design company,
I had a small little vice
and my vice was video games.
I love them. I love to play them.
I love to explore them.
The only problem is I cannot justify
spending time away from my real job
or my family to do something
that doesn't make money.
And when I found Second Life and it did,
wow, I was sold.
I was stuck. I was hooked.
- Well, she makes more money than we do
so, you know, in that sense, yeah.
She's a lot smarter than we are.
- I've been well into the six figure income
and being able to do something you love
and still be at home with your family,
that's pretty much changed my life.
My brother, Steve, I think at times
he's a little jealous of Second Life.
- Jealous? Maybe a little.
I have to go to work.
I work 12 hour shifts.
When you have those days when you
really don't want to get up and go to work
and it's snowing outside and
you have to clean your car,
warm it up, and head to work,
and do it all over again when you leave,
yeah, I'm a little envious.
*I don't think anybody wouldn't be.*
♪ [music] ♪
[motor running]
[waves splashing]
- [Amie] What's been going on? Wow.
[chuckling]
- Oh, a lot of longing and dreaming
and now it's like such a freaking bitch
that we're half a world away because,
you know, it's just such an obstacle now.
I think I need help, Steven.
- You know as our relationship
is progressing, it's been, I don't know,
we're nine or ten months now.
We're still worlds away.
And we get contact like this
or on webcam or on the telephone
and we've had another
physical meeting.
- Yeah. My husband knows
about this last trip and we're...
- And me.
- Yeah.
- And he knows that Second Life
is the --
is the conduit with which
we have come together.
- [sigh] I don't know if I'm gonna
be interrupted here.
- Uhmm, yeah. Hold on please.
*- [Amie's Husband] Is she off to bed?*
*- Yes, she is. Can you give her,
she's supposed to be...*
- [Steven] That's right there, Jason
[chuckles]
- That was my husband
coming down to where my computer is
and, you know, realizing that I —
I'm on, I guess,
a private phone call or whatever,
activity on the computer.
Well, he's, I guess, old fashioned
kind of person
and just has never liked the idea
of the internet, in general.
Thinks it's evil.
He thinks that's why it's called the Web
because like, you know, like an insect
you get stuck in it in like a spider's web.
♪[music]♪
*- [Fiancée] I asked him if he was able
to go on it less,*
but I think for him it's an all or nothing.
I think it would be hard for him to come back
and easier for him to just quit.
- Ayya has said it herself that
in order for me to live my real life,
*she needs to give up hers.*
It was an anguishing decision for her
and the suicide bombings
had a lot to do with that.
She was in a very rational
state of mind that one point.
At the same time,
I was really falling behind in real life.
It was late at night,
I needed to go to sleep.
*She would go in with a tag that says,
"Suicide Bomber"*
*with the explosive vest on,*
*and got a few weapons,
all of the gadgets she had*
*that could do the most damage
to other residents.*
[machine gun firing]
She was going for
innocent people trying to have fun.
So she stopped at beaches, nightclubs,
and places where people are dancing.
[machine gun firing]
[explosion]
It's only looking back at it that
I've been able to put together why,
and the first reason was very practical,
let's get suspended.
If you can't control how much
you're on Second Life,
let's let the Lindens control it.
Let's give them a reason to suspend you.
- [Philip] Well, if people sort of
blow each other up to the point
where they are essentially
denying service,
they're essentially disturbing
the operations of the overall service,
we definitely will kind of take them
out of Second Life
because they're impairing the service.
And really that is the sort of only tool
that we have
as a central government in the world.
*- After about two or three
straight hours of suicide bombings,*
*my account was logged out
by a Linden labs administrator*
*and I received an e-mail that said*
that my account was suspended
for 24 hours.
I was disappointed
because I was hoping for a week.
*- [Philip] The virtual world can only be
successful if it is largely ungoverned.*
And I think the community often wants us
to intervene at times
where it's inappropriate.
And that's something that you actually see
in the emergence of a lot of communities.
There's often a call for governance
that is really,
that would in itself be so stifling
as to restrict the growth
of the whole community.
But, there are frustrating moments where
you really want that to happen.
You don't wanna wait for the emergent
behavior of the society to sort it out.
And I think that that is a difficult
thing to think about
and it causes a lot of friction.
*- [Rohan] Of course, Linden Lab
was in the firing line.*
Whatever they do, there's always gonna
be people that disagree with it
and often for good reasons.
*One of our headlines was
"Sort Second Life Out. Fed up Residents."*
This is a very typical theme
that's very re-occurring in Second Life.
The residents are fed up
that as the platform grows,
*there's of course many problems,
the technical problems.*
*Lin lab don't seem to be able
to keep pace with the change.*
- Crashed.
I crashed again.
Cri-sashed.
*- [Francis Tane] This is Frank. Yeah.*
Hey, how you doing?
In September of 2007. Teasa Copprue
otherwise known as Asri Falcone
came to me for some help with a problem
that was affecting her business.
- I started getting reports that my items
were being spread around the world
*at yard sales and things like that
by people who I had no knowledge*
*of buying my items.*
So, it turned out that they had actually
been stolen and copied and distributed
without my permission.
- [Frank] The belief was that these avatars
were taking advantage of a flaw
in the software underlying Second Life.
*Each on of these virtual spaces,
they're called simulations or an island,*
*resides on a computer server.*
And sometimes for various reasons
for maintenance and also unexpectedly,
*the island or the Sim would crash.*
*When Linden restored that island
or that simulation,*
*sometimes there'd be a duplicate
of those objects made.*
So, if you did it in a systematic way,
you did it one time, you'd have two
*you did again, you'd have four*
and eight and 16 and 32 and 64.
The situation went a lot further
than just Asri.
There were a number of merchants
who believed that they were
being affected
by this copying,
*and they kept seeing Grace Kenzo
as the person making the copies.*
Pretty quickly, in doing some research,
I realized that there was nothing
quite like this on the books.
- You know I found almost
everything I have
and now it's being, you know,
given away as freebies.
I'm like, wait a second.
So, right now I'm not getting
the customers, the sales anymore.
So, I'm kind of in a hole right now
trying to dig my way out.
*- [Amie] We are in New York again,*
*Steven has come from
Fort McMurray in Alberta.*
*This is the first time he has
visited my house.*
♪ [music] ♪
- Very lovely neighborhood.
Very nice house. I'm impressed.
I would like to come here actually
and try to establish a life here.
I'm not sure if that will work out on this side
but it is what we're both thinking about.
- You know, I'm separated now
and divorcing my husband.
And Steven has a separate residence
from his wife, so that's pretty big.
My little area.
- The love den.
*- Love den.*
- Wow, this is it.
- Yeah.
- I recognize this one.
When I saw her basement for the first time,
it was really a deja vu experience.
I had been there.
Yeah, I know.
I recognize it.
It's kind of weird, you know.
Amie rendered a facsimile
of her room in Second Life.
So, she's invited me to it.
And I've in fact walked down the stairs
and been in her basement in Second Life.
- [Amie's Daughter] Here's your community
chest card.
- Are you allowed to read
my community chest card?
This is the first time
that I've met Amie's daughter
and not sure, not sure where it's at just yet.
- [Amie's Daughter] one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten
*- [Steven] Oh, I thought I own that one,
you're lucky.*
*- [Amie] hmm, you're gonna buy it?*
- [Amie's Daughter] Yeah, I'm gonna buy it.
- She's 11 years old,
so she's a little jealous I think
of the relationship that Amie
and I have developed.
- My daughter is not taking so well,
to our spending time together.
*- Yeah.*
- I don't know. I'm surprised.
And then, you know, I don't know.
It's like she wrapped up her own, you know,
her own books to give to you and...
*- Yeah.*
Well, I think too, if we continue with any...
*- I don't know if it's a moral issue.
You know maybe it's the morality of it.*
Maybe she just doesn't see me that way
and now she's kind of seeing, you know,
that I'm not just a mom, I'm a woman, too.
- Are you?
*- [Amie] Interestingly, my daughter
has found her way*
*onto virtual worlds for her --
for her peer group*
*and she has a good time with them.*
*- [Amie's Daughter] Here is my penguin.*
I can't go to my friends,
it's inside of my house.
You know, you could have friends
on Club Penguin.
So, let's see who is this.
*There is one of my friends, Pink Jelly.*
And it's good, meeting friends that
aren't just around your community, right?
You could have a friend that's in Japan,
you know. It's just kind of fun.
♪[music]♪
[typing on keyboard]
- She and I realized that we needed
to get this under control on our own
or deal with the consequences.
Ayya has chosen the date of her deletion,
which is in two weeks,
and that will have been exactly
six months in Second Life.
- [Tea] Right now my business is almost
non-existent.
My income is gone.
And everyone is experiencing
hard times right now.
Well, mainly you have the economy.
The way the world is right now,
people losing jobs in real.
And that affects how much money
you have to put into the game.
So, if the money is not
going back into the game
and it's not there, then, of course,
the economy in game is going to suffer.
*And now that my entire line and everything
is spread throughout SL freely,*
*the value of it have significantly dropped.*
So, I have to build that back up again.
[Swoosh]
- [Asri] This is where I mainly work.
I just made these shoes, actually,
two days ago.
I've actually, you know,
gotten into trying to hire people
but, I mean, how — they can't work
for the rates that I offer
because to be honest, I don't have it.
Since January, I've actually been
living off savings
but my saving is totally depleted now,
it's gone.
And it's gotten to the point where,
if I don't make it
by the end of this month I have to quit.
I really don't wanna do that
because I do love SL so much.
[ringing]
*- [Steven] Hello.*
- Hello. How are you?
Going to sleep now.
Hi.
- How are you?
- I'm good. How are you?
How's your day?
- I missed you.
- I missed you, too.
- Yeah?
Sweetheart, what about me
coming there on my next break?
- When's your next break?
- In seven days.
- Yeah.
I miss you.
I want you.
- Okay, sweetheart I have to go to bed.
I'm gonna turn off my light
but I wanna leave it up,
so that you're there
and I can hear you breathing.
- Okay.
Thank you for sleeping with me.
Makes me feel so close to you.
- I might kiss you, darling.
- I love you, Steven.
- I love you, darling.
Good night my love.
- Good night, sweetheart.
♪[music]♪
- Tomorrow morning is her
6th month birthday in Second Life
and it will be also her last day.
She's been spending her time
catching up and having conversations
with a lot of the people
that mean the most to her,
who she'll never talk to again.
And she is deejaying at the Vortex.
♪[music]♪
- Hi, everybody. Thanks for coming.
- [Ayya] This was gonna be my last song.
But, Gemini said I can keep on going.
- But, Gemini said I can keep on going.
So, I'm taking requests right now
if you want.
- So, I'm taking requests right now
♪ [music] ♪
- It's 2:30 in the morning
and right now one of Ayya's friends
helped her make a dream come true.
She always wanted to fill a house
with beach balls.
And so, he made a machine
that creates — that replicates
beach balls all over the place.
[click, click, click]
- [Ayya] Oh, sweet.
*- [Male Avatar] Yeah, I see a lot of balls.*
- Look at this, look at this.
This is so cool.
This is exactly what I was wanting
to do in this house.
[click, click, click]
♪[music]♪
- It's 6:10 and I've been on at least...
at least 12 hours total.
When the show was over, she went
home to take apart her room
and she had been there ever since
because some friends went with her
and a ton of other friends joined her
at different points.
[typing on keyboard]
*Probably about 20 people
have come through here*
and these same three
have been with her the whole time.
[typing on keyboard]
She's been giving away all the stuff
that she can give to her friends.
The clothing, the toys, the vehicles,
everything she has she's giving —
that she can give away to her friends
she's giving away.
*Snoopy here is a girl,
who she met at Vortex.*
Snoopy right now is very much at a point
that Ayya was early on in Second Life,
where she's just realizing
how deep the addiction runs.
And umm...
and in talking about it, you know,
everyone here sees the value of continuing
and they're struggling between, you know,
what they can get out of continuing
and what they're losing in real life,
in the meantime.
$$ - [Snoopy] When I met Ayya,
I was very much surprised $$
$$ that she is so much interested
in a friendship with me. $$
$$ I thought I cannot believe
that such a cool kid $$
$$ is interested in friendship with me. $$
$$ I felt that this strong feeling
for each other $$
$$ as being the best friends forever,
as Ayya always said. $$
$$ And I was absolutely sure
that Ayya is a girl in real life. $$
$$ We could not imagine that we are
males, both male, in real life. $$
$$ I still remember very much when Ayya
told me that she will leave Second Life. $$
$$ It was a really extreme shock for me. $$
$$ I did not understand
because it felt like, $$
$$ like losing mom and dad
at the same time. $$
$$ I felt like a little kid
losing parents, her parents $$
$$ and it was like having to give up
childhood again. $$
[typing on keyboard]
- I think her friends are a lot sadder
than she is at this point.
I'm feeling excited about it
because I'm looking forward to
just not living to deal with it
but I also think on a deeper level
it means figuring out
how to have her in real life.
She's a part of me.
[typing on keyboard]
- [Male Avatar] Well, in the short time
I got to know Ayya, you know,
Ayya, you've been a pretty good friend.
So, I'm gonna be sorry to see you go.
And it felt like I really should
let you know
how much I appreciated that time.
Again, also people don't forget
it's not just a memorial
to the passing of an avatar
it is a celebration of the fact that
Ayya is still alive and well in the first life.
So, reminder to all of us that she's not
really gone she's just in the real world.
[typing on keyboard]
- I'm just gonna log off
and then I'm gonna log on to her account
in Second Life and cancel it.
[typing on keyboard]
[Ding!]
I deleted Ayya in the — in the only way
that I thought would actually work.
And I know it did because it was
so obviously final to all our friends
and it's obviously final
to me right now, too.
[papers shuffling]
- [Frank] Asri and the other
complainants knew of an avatar
*who was making copies of their items,*
*distributing them, and selling them.*
And they wanted this conduct to stop
and to stop as soon as possible.
[click, click]
*- [Tea] I can make a house and it will
take me five to six months*
*of working eight hours a day to make it.*
And for someone to come along and
take that away from you, it's devastating.
- So, one of the problems
I had to deal with was
who or what were we going to sue.
*It turned out that the real life person*
*behind the avatar was Thomas Simon
of Flushing, New York.*
After some analysis, I knew I had a case.
*What the virtual object really was,
was an item you could see in the world*
*that consisted of graphics*
and sometimes there'd be animation
and sounds associated with it.
So, I knew that those types of works
were protectable as pictorial
or audio visual works
under the *Copyright Act.*
And I knew also, that underlying
all that was a couple of things,
*the machine readable zeros and ones,
and also the human readable source code*
and both types of code were protectable
as literary works under the copyright laws.
- We decided to file a lawsuit
and we actually got six designers together.
*- Including Linda Baca,
otherwise known as Rebel Hope.*
*Shannon Grei, otherwise known as
Munch Flower Isias.*
*Michael Chester, otherwise known as
Doc Aldridge.*
*Kasi Lewis, otherwise known as
Nephilaine Protagonist.*
*And Kevin Alderman,
otherwise known as Stroke Serpentine.*
*These cases were the first instances of
avatars suing other avatars in real life court*
*for intellectual property infringement
occurring within a virtual world.*
Well, the complaint talks about Asri's items
at paragraph 56.
And it says, in pertinent part,
"Two of these products are known
as CFM boots,"
that's item number one
and "Celine Boots," item number two.
Exhibit H is the CFM boots.
That stands for *Cum Fuk Me* boots.
*- [Asri] That's the actual
name of my boots. [laughs]*
*The ultra, ultra high-heel
and sexy footwear.*
♪[music]♪
- Eventually,
we reached a settlement with Mr. Simon
and it contained an injunction
against further copying
and also required Mr. Simon
to pay $525 back to my clients.
*That was what he admitted that he made
selling my clients virtual items.*
The most important takeaway here
when we look back 10 years, 20 years out
is not so much the $525, in my opinion.
It means that virtual worlds are
legitimately part of the real world.
They are governed by the laws
of the real world
and there's not this separation from the
real world that people might think.
[clicking on keyboard]
*- [Steven] I just found a --*
*looks like a pretty interesting spot
right nearby here -- Utopia City.*
[Swoosh]
- [Amie] This is not —
I'm gonna fly up and see.
I can't fly up. What's the hell up with that?
*- [Steven] No fun.*
- No flying?
- That's common, yeah.
Like up there it says, looks like
"No Push, No Rest, No Flying."
- Get out.
- What?
- How can you not let me fly?
- They don't want people to fly.
You never saw that before?
- No. I gotta walk?
- Yeah, is this the State of Utopia?
- I gotta fucking walk?
*See, this is all pointing to the same place.*
*I swear they just changed it.*
Yeah, this was supposed to be Utopia
and it sucks now.
- Well, the big thing is the trip
which I drove from Calgary to New York.
It's happening and I'm here
and I'm pretty excited about it.
*It's gone like I'm already here,
I can't believe it.*
*- [Amie] It's coming up on
our anniversary,*
*a year since we first met
in real life.*
But, we wanna make a home together.
I'm so excited to do that.
- Both of us in our own marriages
have retained lawyers.
We have separation agreements
in the works.
*Time waits for no one,
so it's happening.*
*- [Amie] You know, I've have been
waiting for this time forever.*
Sometimes, I feel like
I've been waiting my whole life.
There were a lot of tears when
it just seemed like the obstacles
weren't gonna, you know, run out.
But, amazingly things just
sometimes fall into place.
This is an extended visit
where Steven and I will really
have a chance to live together
and create that life together,
that sort of new path, that kind of
what we always dreamed about.
And, yeah, there's a lot of mysteries still.
I mean, we don't really have
all the details worked out.
- [Fiancée] I don't blame Second Life.
- Why not?
- Because it's you.
You can't blame something that
you have control over.
We both used it to our advantage
to not deal with the problems.
- But you felt like it was a problem?
- No. Again, there were plenty
of other issues there.
Some that we had dealt with and
some that we are still dealing with
but there are plenty
of issues still there --
- Uh-hm.
- but Second Life was your escape
and it was my chance to have more time
to think or to have more time to...
- It's also something that I tried to talk to you.
Second Life is something
I've tried to talk to you about a ton of times.
And, yeah, you weren't interested
but for me I found parts of myself
that I really needed you to understand.
Now, I don't know if you ever could have.
*- I didn't want to.*
*And I think that that's
what hurt you the most,*
*is that I didn't wanna understand.*
- Umm,
*- Like me not wanting
to understand Second Life,*
*to you translated into "She doesn't
wanna understand me."*
- Oh, yeah. Absolutely, absolutely.
Yeah, you roll your eyes when you say that
but I'm not the only person
that has found themselves there.
And you think that crazy, I know.
I can tell you by the way you're looking at me.
You think that's totally insane.
- I do.
'Cause okay, so five years ago,
what were you without Second Life?
*- I'm not —*
*maybe it's something
I would have discovered,*
*maybe it wasn't but I think
that right now*
and people find it in different ways.
*- No, what you're saying is
Second Life defines you.*
- No, no, absolutely not. I define myself there.
- You define yourself there.
So, yeah. I'm not there.
*I'm here in real life not in Second Life,
so I don't fit into that equation.*
- I was willing to give up anything
to make it work, and um...
one thing this whole experience
taught me was
that I had given up so much of myself
that I was looking for myself
in other places.
My fiancee moved out immediately
when we broke up.
She went to stay with her parents.
I'm packing up now and getting ready
to move somewhere else.
- [Steven] Where do we start?
- [Amie] I really want these boxes
but I'm not ready to just chuck them.
- Since I've arrived, the task I had really
is just trying to establish
a sense of home for me.
It's not awkward but, you know,
I'm moving into Amie and her daughter's
house and home.
And, you know, there are all the
established routines and stuff, you know,
sometimes it's junk,
sometimes it's actual treasures.
Would that work?
*- No.*
- No?
- Ughh!
There's a lot of emotion
attached to some —
a lot of the items that are here
that should be purged.
What if we moved the boxes back here
that are Jimmy's into the garage?
My husband has been out of the house
for six months now,
and he has not removed
all of his items yet.
Okay, that's Jimmy's.
*And, it's difficult to see that around*
*and I'm sure it doesn't feel
very comfortable for Steven.*
This is Jimmy's.
*This is Jimmy's shoes that can go on...*
*- [Steven] This is terrible.*
*- Why?*
*- Are we just gonna stick
this stuff in the garage*
or are we gonna take
the effort to just do it?
*- Put it in the garage.
What do you suggest?*
- I mean, just throw it away.
*- No, we're not going to
throw it away on him.*
- Okay.
- You're a little spoiled by Second Life
and the ease of movement and the —
you know, clutter is not an issue at all.
It just goes into inventory
and disappears.
And real life, you know, isn't like that.
[bottles clanking]
- No. Please, let's just...
- Why are you stressing?
- Because you're going forward
and more is dropping out rather than
when I'm trying to get things contained.
- Well, I asked you if they
could go in there and you said yes.
You know, reality is not Second Life.
There's a lot of things
we can compare or emulate
but here Amie has to get up
and go to work in the morning.
Her daughter has to get up
and be ready for school
and catch the bus.
And so, not that these are problems,
these are real life
and we're just getting into
each others groove to work it.
And I think, we're doing
so far so good.
- I'm less likely to go in
Second Life these days.
For one thing, because
of the technical problems.
There are lag problems or updates
that my computer can't keep up with.
Increased membership,
I guess, creating lag.
But also because I have,
you know, Steven is here
and I'm building a real life with him
and it'd be irresponsible of me
to put my time into that when the —
got to be the only reason I put my time
into that was to spend it with him.
And now he is here and we have
our real challenges to address.
So, this is where I belong now
in the real world with him.
How great to say that, too.
To be able to say,
I'm in the real world with him.
♪[music]♪
- Okay, you know, you're getting
a bad attitude.
*- I am.*
- Why?
- Like I feel like you're just
rushing through this
*- I'm not.*
- and we're having problems.
*- Okay. Alright, alright.*
- Try to go easy, okay?
You really seem a little aggressive.
- I really wish we could use
this stuff, though. So, umm...
- I know, that's what I feel like
- like a little more tender...
*- Alright, alright, alright, alright.*
- And it would have been fine
but, you know...
- But, now it's not.
- Well, I think that's not gonna grow
because it just wasn't...
- Why because the top is broken
and has the leaves there?
But the point is, darling, the point is,
my sweet, look at this fiber, okay.
This I did not break, okay?
This has been sitting here for the week
and the kids did something, okay?
So, if you wanna try to salvage this
and you wanna try to salvage that
we can and this is a plant
and I tell you it's gonna grow, alright?
- Alright. So, I tell you I'm sorry.
- The point is, darling,
we're trying to do something here
and you're fucking griefing me, okay?
So, pick the time to fucking grief me...
- I'm not griefing you.
- Fuck! [chuckles]
- Just, I don't know...
- Continue.
- And you used to be
a little bit more delicate.
*- Here.*
I guess my gardening days are done.
♪[music]♪
- I got to the point where I have to make
a certain amount of money or I was done.
*I couldn't survive anymore.*
By the grace of God,
I don't know how, but I will make it.
[Swoosh]
I'm creating a new line
of whole new existence.
Took me a year, but I got it.
I decided to brand out each line,
meaning my shoe line
is a separate brand.
My clothing line is a separate brand.
*My skin line is a separate brand.*
*Jewelry, hair, all separate brands.*
So, that way, I can more effectively
control my copyrights.
So, I'm making sure that I'm protected.
Well, what I'm really excited about
right now is,
and I think the most exciting,
is my trip to Las Vegas,
to just party and hook it up
with all my friends from Second Life.
Las Vegas Nevada.
♪ [music] ♪
Is that a roller coaster over there?
*- [Driver] Yup. New York, New York.*
*- Really.*
*What, trying to be like Coney Island
or something?*
- [Driver] Yeah, I think so, yeah.
It's a nice one, yeah?
- This is like my third time out here.
And the first two times
I came out here for business.
That was fun but it was
more work than play.
*I had a project.*
*I was hired by Sun Microsystems
to actually recreate*
*part of the strip in Las Vegas.*
*From now on, Vegas will always have
Second Life memories for me.*
*And even more so,
now that I have my friends here.*
We're meeting at the Paris
to go to the Bellagio Fountain
cause she's never seen it before.
*- [Driver] Yeah.*
- Yeah.
*- Yeah, that's nice.
I like Paris. I like Bellagio.*
- I love the Paris. I love it. I love it.
*- You love it?*
- I love it.
*- But have you been to the real Paris?*
- No.
Well, I'm really looking forward
to seeing Misty Roads.
Hey, Honey where are you?
*Misty is an icon of SL.*
*She is pretty much the person responsible
for me being Asri Falcone, I guess.*
Hey, Baby!
Hey, Mis!
Misty, pretty much represents
what community used to be in SL.
*And she helped so many people.*
*I mean, a lot of us wouldn't be here
if it wasn't for her.*
[click, click, click]
- [Misty Road] I'm in Second Life
about 14 hours a day.
This is the longest I've been
out of Second Life. [laughs]
It's my trip here.
Asri said,
"You have to come. You have to come."
Friendships are so important to me,
not only outside of Second Life
but in Second Life
because these people are
my real life friends now.
[water splashing]
Oh, my God, it's too funny.
- I know.
[Laughing]
- And Asri hasn't left my side the whole time.
We've been in cahoots --
gambling, drinking, checking out
the sights,
[camera clicking]
making friends.
[Shrieking and laughing]
- How are you doing?
- Wonderful, wonderful!
*- [Tea] You know, your real life friends
don't always get you.*
You know, so, it's nice to be around
a lot of people who can get --
get you and understand you
and not judge you because
you are on a virtual world, you know.
*- Within a week of the time that
I split up with my fiancee,*
*I was back in Second Life as a boy.*
And it felt like the old Ayya was giving up,
was giving in, and conceding to me
*allowing me to be more myself.*
As a boy avatar, I reconnected with a girl
who had been Ayya's sister before
*and we became now, brother and sister.*
*And we would talk at night before bed,*
before I would go to sleep
and I was able to say it out loud to her
what I could never say out loud to myself,
which was that as a child,
I had been a victim of abuse
and the memories were there,
I was just pretending they weren't.
It was always known in my family that,
on both sides of my family,
that my father molested the kids.
And it was always known
but not talked about.
And it was assumed, I guess,
that it was only the girls.
And it was very convenient for me
to assume that I was lucky.
But, this memory always came back
and it was something I ignored.
By pretending it didn't happen,
it didn't make the anger go away.
It was there anyway
and it found it's way out through Ayya.
- Okay. You there?
Okay.
Since we last talked, you know,
the big change is
I'm no longer in New York,
I'm now back in Calgary.
You know, my intention was
to try to seek employment
in New York
but immigration and work status
and all that is proving
a little difficult also.
I'm not sure if I said this back
in the beginning of the summer
when we filmed in New York.
You know, it was a good
test period for us.
And we had a lot of ups and downs.
And again, primarily, the stress
of the divorce
and the battle between
her husband and the child and me
you know, all trying
to make that work out
now that we've worked through it,
we're now...
You know, we're committed.
We're, Amie and I, are committed
to one another.
We did the long distance relationship
for quite some time.
So, I don't want to do it
for a long time again
but if that's what it takes,
that's what we're gonna do.
If we didn't break out of Second Life,
who knows?
*We got our own little world in there*
*and I bet you we'd have
a nice little house.*
*And we'd have a bigger
community of friends.*
♪[music]♪
But, we broke free.
- He wasn't trying to stay together.
He went off to fucking India. [sniffles]
If he was trying to stay together,
he would have made a home
for me to come to in India.
I -- this is too emotionally raw for me
to be able to, you know,
speak objectively about it.
He's fake.
And I'm real. [sighs]
And I hurt.
And he is living scot free.
I want to get across that I'm a victim.
*And that doesn't mean I'm stupid.*
*I believed he was really
the person he presented.*
*But, that's a silly notion on my part
because he's not real.*
♪ [music] ♪
- I call Second Life the best
and the worst thing
that has ever happened to me.
It's the worst thing because
of the people that I let down
in the meantime while I was
pursuing this journey.
And it is very sad to lose what has been,
til now, the love of my life.
But, it's the best thing because
it made me completely rethink
and rediscover who I am.
Everything about my mind
and the way I work
and everything about my past
makes more sense now.
And everything about I want
for the future makes more sense.
♪[music]♪
I feel like I'm gonna be
in virtual worlds forever
and there's nothing that can
keep me out of them.
♪[music]♪
- [Philip] Having thought about this
for some time
and having seen, you know, everything
unfolding and growing in Second Life
I would say that to a certain extent,
the virtual world must contain some
sort of danger and risk
and possibility of pain or loss
to be interesting.
I don't think that we can create
worlds of any kind that aren't —
that are interesting without them
also being, you know,
at least somewhat dangerous.
That said, the virtual world is
at a basic level
a safer place than the real world.
We do not have the ability
in the virtual world
to physically harm each other.
And that is a very powerful change
that I think brings us closer
to our aspiration about
what it is to be human.
I think that the fact that we are
perhaps emotionally in danger
but not physically in danger
in the virtual world is
a tremendous positive step
toward being all that we can be.
So, while the virtual world
is not without danger
it's certainly a good deal safer
than the physical world
that we, for the most part live in now.
♪[music]♪